i mean ask yourself can you stop your
feeling can you stop your form from
deteriorating can you prevent perceptions from
can you prevent perceptions from
besetting you
can you not choose
well samsara is usually translated as a
rebirth but it's really um literally
but it's really um literally
the meaning of samsara means to wander
on
keep wandering onwards just keep going
keep going
so and it is a better
it's it certainly sheds clearer light on
the idea of samsara than the word
rebirth because rebirth means like this life and
because rebirth means like this life and
then the next life
and then in that in between is just me
sort of passing from one life to the
other but it's not really that you're being
but it's not really that you're being
reborn it's more like just you still are
just here and there and elsewhere
on and on and on the simulator would the
buddha would give with
us like a man who went one with one
village and from that village later on he went
and from that village later on he went
to another one and then to another one
and then to another one and then to
another one so it's still like
the man just going through all these
different places you here now and then
somewhere else like without these
memories without these recognitions
but same sort of set of aggregates
same point of view he's just wandering
on
like you go to sleep you wake up another
day then you go to sleep you wake up as
an animal
i mean i'm overly simplifying it but i
want to illustrate it it's
that's like sometimes reflecting upon
samsara in the suttas
would have an impact on people in a
sense of i better practice
because if you talk about the rebirths
it's sort of out of your hands
it's just how the universe works you
just come you
you just reborn here and there but the
birth in itself it's not the beginning
so if you think from that point of view
you realize like well imagine like for
example if now
if somebody would offer to you would you
start this life
again say you go back and become a
toddler without having being able to keep all
without having being able to keep all
the memories and everything you've been
through that you know now
that has to be raised would you go
through the same ordeal again
just in the life that you already know
let alone a realm that you have
not familiar with or something like that
and actually when you think about it
usually the appeal is behind oh i'll
keep my memories and then i can start
the same
like when people think about and that's
when they think about rebirth as if
you know you take things with you and so
on and then
you better yourself through rebirth no
it's just erasing
but but you're still there so just
somebody wipes you clean and then you
start again
knowledge has gone as well the stuff
that you learn and
and experienced so would you want to do
it again then
and then it will make you think twice
because you might make even worse
choices than you did in your life that
pressure of having to choose having to act being
of having to choose having to act being
in the environment
it's like in hindsight it can be
pleasant but when it's there it's never
pleasant so if you realize that samsara is that
so if you realize that samsara is that
point of view
that you are bound with and then you
will like unless you develop wisdom and and
like unless you develop wisdom and and
practice them correctly that you will be
then just
repeating it on and off just wiping the
slate clean here and there and elsewhere
but still going through the same things
on and on
and on and on
and that's with a man there is nobody
there is nothing that you haven't been
already beings have been in sasara for
so long that is
you've been everything you've been
mother and the father and the killer and
the killed and
every enemy you've been everything
you've been around so long the tedious
repetition that you have no memory of that's
that you have no memory of that's
basically what samsara is
so then you realize this life is not
like oh now i'm
born samsara is waiting for me no this
is already
that wandering on it's one of many
wandering on
and the directions you choose based on
your actions and choices you make
are the directions you will wander on
later it's setting you up for it
that's why beings are the owners of
their actions and you know the actions
you uh the choices you make things you
do
determine then where you're heading
well you are not in samsara is not the
universe that you inhabit
samsara is your experience as a whole so
what you have now
is what samsara is so in the same sense
you can recognize certain
tedious repetition of like day-to-day
things just extend that into infinite
just extend that into infinite
extend it like into the next life and
next life and so on
day month year 100 years is just
repetition perpetually just repeating because
perpetually just repeating because
you kind of you forget you lapse you
lose the memory of
and that's what would have said even if
somebody can remember the previous lives
the previous wanderings on the
directions they've been in
all they would remember is these five
aggregates that they have now
so the five aggregates which is your
experience as a whole matter
feeling perception intentions
consciousness there is nothing outside
of that
samsara is that it's the aggregates that
are bound with ignorance to keep
repeating basically infinitely infinite until
basically infinitely infinite until
until until you make the effort and
maybe uproot that division
yeah the content changes while the
aggregates remain the same
and that's the whole point village that
village the point is you are still wandering on
the point is you are still wandering on
so it doesn't mean you don't have and
it's not like oh this is metaphorically
speaking samsari is already here
no factually this what what this life
thought it is
it's already wandering on i mean ask
yourself can you stop your feeling can you stop
can you stop your feeling can you stop
your form from deteriorating
can you prevent perceptions from
besetting you
can you not choose can you not become
can you switch off your consciousness
you have no say in any of these
aggregates they're just flowing already
coming and going so to speak taking
directions
so that's already what samsara is you
don't need the belief
and proof of next life because you're
already not in control of these
aggregates and they're already taking you in
and they're already taking you in
directions that often you don't even
want to go
and certainly forcing you to endure
things so here's the samsara you don't get it
so here's the samsara you don't get it
more directly than that
so yeah death is not the end in birth is
not not the beginning
it's just like rearrangement of the same
thing another way of repeating it so you don't
another way of repeating it so you don't
need a memory of previous lives or
or like a a special insight into future
lives to see some sarah
as wandering on already something you're
fully engaged as we speak
well yeah you are doing it and you can't
just stop it
because there will be another choice
within the samsara
another choice within the aggregate of
choice within the aggregate of sankara
can you not choose
can you abstain from choice without that
being another choice
you can't so you're fully within it you
have to do it
can you not feel is that even
conceivable can you imagine your your existence in
can you imagine your your existence in
the most abstract terms
without the form without the body
enduring there
impossible inconceivable so you're fully
under the weight and control of the
aggregates for which direction you're only
for which direction you're only
responsible like
you can't control them you can't stop
them you can't tell your aggregates go
this way or that way
but you can only then start making the
choices of
of a wholesome kind as opposed to
choices of unwholesome kind
and in that indirect manner maybe
improve the state of your aggregates and
so on and you can again
not in six lifetimes in this life as
well if a person starts practicing sense
if a person starts practicing sense
restraint they will naturally their mind
will develop more patience
more calmness more self-composure more
self-restraint and strength
and that's already something that will
make this wandering on in this life
much more endurable much more agreeable
as well
would like is being impatient suffering
is being impatient pleasant or
unpleasant it's very unpleasant
when you want something you can't get it
or you don't want something but you
can't get rid of yet to endure it
you're not patient but is that patience
given or you develop it either by
or you develop it either by
circumstances forcing it upon you and
you have no choice about it
or actually if you foresee it and start
making effort in the direction of
developing patients
there's just one example so by making
choices of of wholesome kind in this life by
of of wholesome kind in this life by
not pursuing sensuality sort of
carelessly without any restraint without
any regard for others
not being immoral not being non-virtuous
not being
harmful to others by making that effort
to keep yourself in check
you're actually developing patience
which means the endurance of this
samsara or this wandering on
you will be able to tolerate it more
the pressure as well because you learned
it you developed that tolerance
and that's the thing tolerance can needs
to be developed it's not
god given quality if you invest effort
in it it will grow if you don't it will
shrink and then you will be even more pulled by
and then you will be even more pulled by
the aggregates by the desires
by the feelings and then you're
wandering on will be even faster
more hectic more distracted like an
animal and that's why when rearrangement of the
and that's why when rearrangement of the
these
this form occurs but your mind was the
mind of an animal pretty much
that's the form you're going to be
assuming that's what i said if somebody behaves
that's what i said if somebody behaves
like an animal in this life that's
around their head and
if you're behaving even worse that's
wrong no not the realm
like again figure of speech not the
realm as this place that waits for you
it's just
you're wandering on when he has this
like a wiping of that slate clean and
restarting it
that will be the form there will be the
means of engagement that it assumes
because that's what the mind has been
cultivating because that's what the body is by the
because that's what the body is by the
way it's like means of engagement with
the world in in the sense objects
so what you chose to engage with the way
you chose to engage with your body
that's basically where your mind is
heading so next time you might get
something you might get a body that's more
you might get a body that's more
suitable for the level of engagement
that you want and expect
so if your mind was engaging with sense
objects on the level of like animal
passion and madness and thirst you're going to
and madness and thirst you're going to
get a body that's much more suitable
that's why dogs have a smell 500
times stronger than humans because
that's how much
how many times they're more pulled by
the sense objects than humans
500 times
you might smell something nice but will
not make you lose your mind well dog
will lose its mind
but if you don't make the effort and you
start giving in to losing your mind on
account of sense objects
yeah you're going to get senses then
they will support that what you want
basically what you keep choosing
or if you like develop sort of choices
they will they will abstain from sense
objects then you don't need sense organs so when
then you don't need sense organs so when
the
rearrangement happens so to speak you're
gonna get much less of sense organs
so like in the sutures when the buddha
would describe the celestial type of
bodies that are not they're much more refined
that are not they're much more refined
not you wouldn't even call them bodies
from our point of view where the body is
but again future life previous life
doesn't matter what matters is to
recognize the nature of
aimless wandering on
and any aim you might have within that
wandering arm
is fundamentally aimless so even if you
have some great purpose in this life
mundane purpose not purpose of
enlightenment it's it's it's a mundane purpose which
it's it's it's a mundane purpose which
means it's not it's not really changing
the state of that aimless wandering on
so your aim is only relative and
when the time comes for for things to
rearrange they will and you will that aim will
they will and you will that aim will
make make no difference
in other words you cannot prevent form
from deforming
getting sick and dying just
inconceivable so you don't borrow time every time so
so you don't borrow time every time so
if you if you want to have like a like a
simplified example of what we could
respond to
rebirth it's not about being born again
or dying it's really about losing the
memory and that's why beings are bound to like
and that's why beings are bound to like
constant pointless repetition of the
same things because they have no
recollection that they already done this
billions of times because if you did you
wouldn't want to do it anymore
you would really want to leave that
state of affairs imagine now somebody
comes and wipes your memory just the
memory so your body is still intact
you're still alive but completely
utterly your memory recognition anything in
your memory recognition anything in
everything you know including yourself
is gone
so for you if you were to wake up from
that state although the like somebody
can see externally would see yeah it's
still the same person same body but from
your point of view
the body everything it would be a new
thing but it's not a new thing isn't it but
but it's not a new thing isn't it but
it's a new thing
from that internal point of view because
you have no memory of it
and that's exactly what rebirth is he's
just losing the memory of recognizing
that it's not and the aggregates are not
new never work you're just going to keep
going and going ignorance in regard to
it has no beginning
so that's why like you should be
concerned about death and dying
is because everything you learn even the
wisdom you got
unless it was of a substantial kind will
most likely not play much
part then all you can do and that's what
everybody would say like
if people wanted to have a better
rebirth you focus on doing wholesome
things because as i explained simply by
because as i explained simply by
cultivating certain habits in the mind
when your memory is wiped clean
you're gonna start using the body from
the point of view of the habits you
cultivated before
so you don't have explicit memory of the
habits but the inclinations are there
and inclinations in this life yeah
you're responsible for but as
inclinations they're probably because
you've been
choosing those things many times before
so it doesn't mean that you can now just
carelessly give in to inclinations
just means the presence of inclination
is due to previous habits
which then also means you could reshape
them if your inclinations are bad
double down in doing good things in this
life so you develop good inclinations
so then in the next life those
inclinations will be what what
inclines you and directs you without
that wisdom without
memory to to recall on so that's really
that's really what that
rebirth within samsara is and making you
start again without knowing that you're
starting again
it's it's like the best trick